Today's and
good חודש chodesh so appropriately look at that on ראש חודש Rosh
Chodesh we're learning about קידוש החודש. Kiddush HaChodesh. Today's דף daf is
כב. Chaf Beis. We pick up on the משנה mishna on כא
עמוד ב Chaf Aleph Amud Beis and we are going to continue
both at the end of this פרק perek and the beginning of
the next dealing with these issues about קידוש החודש. Kiddush HaChodesh. Going
to be interesting that
we have a whole break of a פרק perek but the conversation
will just continue straight. Okay so that's coming up but let's pick
up where we left off on כא
עמוד ב. Chaf Aleph Amud Beis. בין שנראה בעליל בין שלא נראה
בעליל Bein shenira be'alil bein shelo nira be'alil so we have learned
that you can even violate שבת Shabbat in order to come and
testify about the new moon not in order to send out the
messengers that you would not violate שבת Shabbat but in order for
the witnesses to come so you could so you could sanctify it
in its right time based on the witnesses that you would violate
שבת Shabbat
and particularly for תשרי Tishrei and ניסן Nissan which the ימים טובים
Yamim Tovim are dependent on except in time of the בית המקדש
Beis HaMikdash you would do it for all of the ראשי חדשים
Rashei Chadashim but afterwards only for ניסן Nissan and תשרי. Tishrei. This
משנה mishna says whether the new month was seen בעליל be'alil which
we'll see in the גמרא Gemara means clearly or whether it was
not seen clearly מחללין עליו את השבת. mechallelin alav es HaShabbat. The
witnesses can come because you might say look it was a beautiful
new moon clear night everybody saw it. Why should I be entitled
to violate שבת Shabbat to go to the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash
to testify if I am sure that there are people that live
closer that saw it and won't have to violate שבת Shabbat so
it shouldn't give me license to go and violate שבת. Shabbat. No
everybody should come anybody who's seen it you violate שבת Shabbat to
come and to come. You never know what's going to happen and
maybe everybody else for some reason will be invalid and you'll be
the only one that whose on whose testimony it will rely.
מחללין mechallelin means you should.
Yes yeah that's true it's not just mean you may it means
that you should meaning well you shouldn't go out of your way
to be מחלל שבת mechallel Shabbat but
right a cigarette on the way.
Exactly no but it means right meaning that's true implicit in this
is for giving you license to be מחלל שבת mechallel Shabbat it's
not like if you feel like going up to testify for קידוש
החודש Kiddush HaChodesh yeah no it means you have to go if
you've seen it of course you do wonder what happens in those
cases like really like let's say everybody saw it right so forget
חילול שבת Chillul Shabbat like a hundred thousand people are supposed to
come and testify like I don't really get that exactly. Alright anyway
רבי יוסי אומר Rabbi Yosi omer רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi says אם
נראה בעליל אין מחללין עליו את השבת im nira be'alil ein mechallelin
alav es HaShabbat
no if it were seen clearly then you do not violate שבת
Shabbat definitely there'll be somebody else around to come and testify. מעשה
שעברו יותר מארבעים זוג Ma'aseh she'avru yoser me'arba'im zug there was a
time when more than forty people
passed through you know that they came to testify
ועכבם רבי עקיבא בלוד ve'ikvam Rabbi Akiva beLod
and רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva held them up at the airport okay
and he basically did not let them go from לוד Lod to
ירושלים Yerushalayim to testify. Why? Because he said look so many people
have seen it we don't need all you guys other people will
go and they'll testify and you don't need to violate שבת. Shabbat.
Now by the way how far is לוד Lod from ירושלים? Yerushalayim?
It is not close right?
What do you mean it's not close? It's close.
No by horse it's not close right? How what is it 40
miles or something? Yeah so I don't get it how they're getting
there on שבת Shabbat and going to be able to testify you
know that before the day is over which is when you need
them to testify by horse can you get it? I mean when
did they come? They didn't come presumably the night did they come
in the middle of the night? I don't know so I don't
get it exactly now maybe when when the בית Beis when maybe
when they did the קידוש החודש Kiddush HaChodesh in יבנה Yavne where
is יבנה Yavne exactly?
Right in the middle of the country. Further from
לוד? Lod? Further a snip further from לוד? Lod?
Aha further right from לוד? Lod? That's what I'm asking is יבנה
Yavne closer to לוד? Lod? Yes yes so then that probably makes
sense because רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is post חורבן הבית Churban HaBayis
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is when the center is in יבנה Yavne
so that makes sense so that makes sense that they're going on
their way to יבנה. Yavne.
Okay anyone who saw the moon can testify I for some reason
all these years thought that the עדים eidim were like designated
no they weren't designated we'll see in a minute about they have
to בית דין Beis Din has to know who they are because
they might be sectarians who are trying to manipulate the calendar but
they do not have to be designated we'll get that that's coming
up that's coming up okay but that makes sense that they're on
their way to יבנה. Yavne. Okay שלח לו רבן גמליאל shalach lo
Rabban Gamliel so רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel sent him אם מעכב אתה
את הרבים נמצאת מכשילם לעתיד לבוא im me'akeiv atta es harabbim nimtza
makhshilam le'asid lavo if you basically prevent the masses from coming and
maybe specifically masses there are so many next year you're going to
cause them to stumble because next year they'll say why should I
שלעפ shlep last year I went that whole way and I even
violated שבת Shabbat and then they told me not to do the
rest of the way so you know it was a שלעפ shlep
and it caused me to do חילול שבת Chillul Shabbat forget it
I'm not going to do it. So no you have to. to
go ahead and let them do it. Which, by the way, is
interesting, the way in which sort of policy considerations, or I should
say sort of macro
issues, warrant the violation of שבת. Shabbat. Meaning, are we necessarily saying
that right now your coming is necessary for קידוש החודש Kiddush Hachodesh
and therefore can override שבת? Shabbat? Presumably no. Presumably we're not debating
it, you could phrase it that way, maybe I'll need you, maybe
everybody else won't work out. But that wasn't what רבן גמליאל Rabban
Gamliel said. רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel said, long-term, big picture, it's necessary
to have this policy in place in order to ensure that we
will do קידוש החודש בזמנו. Kiddush Hachodesh bizmano. Because without this type
of an institution of letting everybody come or whatever, it'll just sort
of, you know, it'll just prevent it from happening. So that means
the חילול שבת chilul Shabbat is warranted, not necessarily because of this
micro case in front of us, but because of the more like
macro considerations. You know, it gets to these whole questions about התיבו
סופם משום תחילתם, hativu sofam mishum techilatan, right,
which is like, you know, the drivers, people driving back home, the
doctors after they go to the hospital on שבת, Shabbat, where the
driving back home certainly has nothing to do with saving a life.
Now, there's a big debate about that, when the גמרא Gemara had
that in ביצה, Beitzah, it was about דרבנן, d'rabbanan, not about דאורייתא,
d'oraisa, you know, to allow something after the fact and so on.
But nevertheless, it's interesting that, you know, that it seems to be
here certain, like I said, sort of macro policy considerations saying because
of the bigger picture of in order to get this done בזמנו,
bizmano, we should be, you know, should allow שבת Shabbos to be
overwritten right here.
That's like having every couple sign a pre-nuptial agreement not because I'm
concerned about them but because we want to institutionalize the policy.
Right, right. Well, there are always issues for policy issues. My question
is a policy
translating into allowing שבת Shabbat to be overwritten. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara says like this: מאי משמע דהאי עליו? Mai mashma dehai
alio? Where do you get this idea that the word עליו alio
is לישנא דמיגלי הוא, lishna d'migli hu, a language of being revealed?
Like, it's clear to everyone. אמר רבי אבא אמר קרא, Amar Rabbi
Abba, Amar kra, says the verse: אמרות ה' אמרות טהורות כסף צרוף
בעליל לארץ מזוקק שבעתיים. Imrot Hashem imrot tehorot, kesef tzaruf b'alil la'aretz
mezukak shivatayim.
The words of God, the utterances of God, are pure utterances, like
purified silver בעליל b'alil la'aretz. Now, בעליל לארץ. b'alil la'aretz. Now I
must tell you that in at least the English translation I looked
at yesterday, בעליל לארץ b'alil la'aretz was translated as a crucible, as
an earthenware crucible. Crucible. Thank you. As an earthenware crucible. So עליל
alil is the thing in which you are being מצרף, metzaref, the
thing in which you are smelting the silver, which makes sense in
the context. But somehow the גמרא Gemara understands the word בעליל b'alil
like it's pure. God's utterances are pure, like, you know,
like smelted
silver, בעליל, b'alil, looked at clearly, or somehow in its purity. Somehow
they're reading the word בעליל b'alil here as purity or clearly. And
then I don't know what they do with the word לארץ, la'aretz,
you know, on the- so I'm not sure how according to that
read what לארץ la'aretz is doing there. מזוקק שבעתיים, Mezukak shivatayim,
you know, refined seven times. So anyway, it means pure, refined, clear,
that's what the word בעליל b'alil means. So that's how we get
that idea. I think that's even in modern Hebrew, right? נראה בעליל?
Nirah b'alil? No? Yes! Right. All right. So רב ושמואל, Rav v'Shmuel,
so a debate of רב Rav and שמואל. Shmuel. חד אמר, Chad
amar, one says: נ' שערי בינה נבראו בעולם. Nun sha'arei bina nivra'u
ba'olam. There were fifty levels or gates of wisdom created in the
world, וכולן ניתנו למשה. v'kulan nitnu l'Moshe. And משה Moshe had all
of this. חסר אחת, Chasar achat, minus one, he had forty-nine. Okay,
famous מדרש. Midrash. שנאמר ותחסרהו מעט מאלוקים. Shene'emar: vatachasrehu me'at me'elokim. You
have-
you have taken him down, you know, deprived him a little bit
from the level of God. He only had forty-nine levels, a little
bit he was below the divine. Now what does that have to
do with anything? It has to do with the fact that the
פסוק pasuk says, 'Imrot Hashem mezukak shivatayim,' and shivatayim meaning seven sevens.
Very appropriate for שבועות Shavuos coming up. So seven sevens is forty-nine.
So therefore משה Moshe achieved the שבעתיים, shivatayim, the forty-nine levels that
were achievable by human beings.
Okay, now based on this, so what's the debate of רב Rav
and שמואל? Shmuel? So the debate of רב Rav and שמואל's Shmuel
not the first line, but it's then how that ties into the
second part of the discussion. ביקש קהלת למצוא דברי חפץ. Bikesh Kohelet
limtzo divrei chefetz. So-
so
קהלת Kohelet desired to find words of desire or matters of desire,
the matters of his desire. Let's see what that means. ביקש קהלת,
Bikesh Kohelet, קהלת Kohelet desired,
להיות כמשה, l'hiyot k'Moshe, to be like משה. Moshe. Right? He wanted
to have that same level of wisdom. And קהלת Kohelet was supposed
to be the wisest of all men. יצאה בת קול ואמרה לו,
Yatza bas kol v'amrah lo, so a heavenly voice came out and
said to him: וכתוב יושר דברי אמת. v'chasuv yosher divrei emet. Okay,
which is the end of the פסוק. pasuk. So wait, where's וכתוב
יושר דברי אמת? v'chasuv yosher divrei emet? Is that the end of
that פסוק? pasuk?
I think it was the same פסוק. pasuk. What?
From ביקש קהלת למצוא דברי חפץ. Bikesh Kohelet limtzo divrei chefetz. Right,
right, yes. The end of the פסוק. pasuk. Oh, ביקש קהלת למצוא
דברי חפץ. Bikesh Kohelet limtzo divrei chefetz. What? Yes, yeah. So anyway
and it's and it's written what is written sort of proper, the
words of truth. What does that mean?
So what's דברי אמת? divrei emet? What's written sort of straight away
in the words of truth? That's in the תורה. Torah. And what
does it say in the תורה? Torah? ולא קם נביא עוד בישראל
כמשה. velo kam navi od b'Yisrael k'Moshe. So you're sorry buddy, you
can't be like משה. Moshe. You want to למצוא דברי חפץ? limtzo
divrei chafetz? Look at the תורה, Torah, you can't be like משה.
Moshe. So that's what one of them says. משה Moshe had the
49 levels, not קהלת. Kohelet. ואחד אמר, v'achad amar, the other one
says, בנביאים לא קם. b'neviim lo kam. No, no, no, that wouldn't
be a problem. It says לא קם נביא עוד בישראל. lo kam
navi od b'Yisrael. There was no נביא, navi, nobody who reached the
level of משה's Moshe נבואה. nevuah. במלכים קם. bimelachim kam. With kings
he could. Now it could just mean oh technically he wasn't a
נביא navi so he was excluded from this rule, but I think
it could also mean that nobody reached משה's Moshe level of נבואה.
nevuah. It doesn't mean that nobody could reach משה's Moshe level of
wisdom. So actually, so that wasn't or leadership, but here the point
is wisdom. So that wasn't a problem. אלא, ela, so he was
entitled, so he had the 49 levels of wisdom. So not only
משה, Moshe, even קהלת. Kohelet. אלא מאי אני מקיים ביקש קהלת למצוא
דברי חפץ? ela mai ani mekayem bikesh kohelet limtzo divrei chafetz? So
what do I do with this sense that he wanted but then
the end of the פסוק pasuk seems to say it wasn't given
to him? ביקש קהלת לדון דינים שבלב שלא בעדים ושלא בהתראה. bikesh
kohelet ladun dinim shebalev shelo b'edim v'shelo b'hatra'ah. קהלת Kohelet because he
was so wise and he could understand people's deepest motivations and thoughts,
he wanted to run his court based on his perception of what
people's motivations and inner thoughts were without external evidence, without testimony, without
witnesses. I'll figure it all out. יצאה בת קול ואמרה לו, yatza
bat kol v'amra lo, so a heavenly voice came out and said
וכתוב יושר דברי אמת. v'katuv yosher divrei emet. You have to look
at the proper words written in the words of truth in the
תורה. Torah. על פי שנים עדים יקום דבר. al pi shnayim edim
yakum davar. Okay, which is interesting, which means you might be very
wise but that doesn't mean that we can run our world based
on your insight. Okay, the world and the court system still have
to be run based on objectively ascertainable facts. So interesting little sort
of, you know, issue going on there about where to draw the
limit in terms of his own ability of intellectual achievement or in
terms of trying to apply, you know, sort of like the story
with רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, that רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, you know,
we didn't פסקן pasken like רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir because he was
so smart but nobody could figure out what he was talking about.
He was too smart for the rest of us. So it's all
very nice you're so brilliant but that's not going to impact how
we as mere mortals are going to run our like legal system
and our world. Okay anyway that was a bit of a digression.
Moving on. מעשה שעברו יותר מארבעים זוג ועיכבן רבי עקיבא. maaseh she'avru
yoter me'arbaim zug v'ikvan Rabbi Akiva.
So רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva held up over 40 pairs of witnesses
in לוד. Lod. תניא tanya it says on a ברייתא, braita, אמר
רבי יהודה amar Rabbi Yehuda חס ושלום chas v'shalom שרבי עקיבא עיכבן.
she'Rabbi Akiva ikvan. It would never have occurred to רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva to hold them, he understood the idea that you violate שבת
Shabbat and you would never have said oh they're too many. אלא
שזפר ראש של גדר עיכבן. ela Shazpar rosh shel gader ikvan.
This other person שזפר Shazpar the head of the גדר. Gader. I
don't know where גדר, Gader, where's גדר? Gader? Is גדר Gader what's
called...
גדרה, Gedera,
is close to what's called גדרה Gedera today. Is that close to
לוד? Lod? It's near the coast, it's closer to the coast. Near
אשקלון. Ashkelon. Got it. ושלח רבן גמליאל והורידו מגדולתו.
vishalach Rabban
Gamliel v'horidu migedulato.
And רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel
sort of got this guy deposed from his political post because of
this because of this activity. Quite interesting, quite a different story than
than just being רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. Now another interesting question which
is not explicit here but I assume implicit is that this violating
of שבת Shabbat is only going to be if we're making the
month a 29 day month, we're making it, we're being מקדש החודש,
mekadesh hachodesh, right as opposed to making it an עיבור. ibur. Normally
the phrase מקדשו mekadesho means you do it, you make the previous
month small and you do it on day 30 ראש חודש Rosh
Chodesh as opposed to being מעבר החודש meaber hachodesh making it pregnant
is the 30 day
ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh and you make ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh on
day 31. Because if that happened, if it was not seen on
day 30 and day 31 is going to be ראש חודש, Rosh
Chodesh, why would you violate שבת? Shabbat? Obviously day 31 is going
to be ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh. Now it does raise the issue
that we saw before, right, if you remember the גמרא Gemara about
is there an idea
of being מקדש החודש על פי הראיה mekadesh hachodesh al pi hare'iyah
even on day 31, to the point that it's מצווה, mitzvah, you
know it's a מצווה mitzvah to do it still based on testimony.
Would that be enough of you know, and to do that even
in order to violate שבת? Shabbat? But one does wonder if the
same issues would take place if it was pure totally clear and
hundreds of people saw it, would that be enough justification even on
day 31 when there was no question that today was ראש חודש
Rosh Chodesh and they were going to make today ראש חודש Rosh
Chodesh anyway? So would or is it particularly that that mandate you
know is on day 30 when it makes a difference whether you're
going to do it today or tomorrow. So I think that's not
fully explicated here it did come up a little bit the other
like two days ago about מצווה לקדש על פי הראיה. mitzvah lekadesh
al pi hare'iyah. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like because again
the ברייתא braita quoted earlier just to remind you was על שני
חודשים מחללין את השבת על ניסן ועל תשרי. al shnei chodashim mechalelin
et hashabbat al nisan v'al tishrei. Sorry no that's different. Anyway that
was in a conversation of whether it was 29 and 30 days.
So the גמרא Gemara did recognize that the idea of... Doing it
על פי הראיה al pi hare'iyah could be enough justification to violate
שבת Shabbat even if it was a
מלא, maleh, but my guess, my question is whether that would be
even if it was like hundreds of people saw it, would even
that be enough of a justification if you knew that today was
ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh regardless? Okay, let's take a look now at
the next משנה. mishna. אב ובנו, ab u-beno, now we're getting to
who can testify. אב ובנו שראו את החודש ילכו. ab u-beno she-ra'u
et ha-chodesh yelechu. So even if a father and son saw they
can go. Why? You can't have relatives testify. לא שמצטרפין זה עם
זה, lo she-mitztarfin zeh im zeh, not because they can combine together
to testify, אלא שאם יפסל אחד מהם מצטרף השני עם אחר. ella
she-im yippasel echad mehem mitztaref ha-sheni im acher. If one of them
becomes invalidated, maybe because he says the wrong thing and he doesn't
get the exact details right, at least there'll be the second one,
which makes total sense. If you're going to accept a hundred witnesses,
you don't need all hundred, so you're having more people come than
the bare minimum because some of them might not work out. So
if that's true, the same is true of father and son who
travel together. It's no different than ten people traveling together, you don't
need all ten. So here too, maybe one of them won't work
out and you'll use the other one.
Yeah, one of the things like when we want to do קידוש
לבנה, Kiddush Levanah, you walk outside and sometimes you can see it
and sometimes you can't. Some neighborhood you can see it, then another
neighborhood you can't. You think if a whole village saw it rather
than a thousand people getting up and moving, they say okay you
stay שמעון. Shimon.
Again
that's what I don't get.
I agree
with you, I agree with you, like I said if you have
no limits, what happens if it's totally clear
like a hundred thousand people are going to go? Now again, I
don't know because when the moon is just it's brand new, it's
like very small, so maybe maybe but again so what if it's
small? If it's a clear night out and everybody sees it, like
I agree, I don't get it.
The בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash has room for all these people that
move. Exactly.
Alright,
moving on. So it says like this, okay. רבי שמעון אומר אב
ובנו וכל הקרובים כשרים לעדות החודש. Rabbi Shimon omer ab u-beno ve-kol
ha-kerovim kesherim le-edut ha-chodesh.
So he doesn't deny the first line, that's obvious if you'll take
tons of people will go a father and son should go. But
he goes even further: a father and son and all relatives are
kosher. We'll see why in the גמרא. Gemara. אמר רבי יוסי מעשה
בטוביה הרופא, amar Rabbi Yosi ma'aseh bi-Tuvyah ha-rofe,
there's a story with טוביה Tuvyah the doctor שראה את החודש בירושלים,
she-ra'ah et ha-chodesh bi-Yerushalayim, he saw it in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, הוא ובנו
ועבדו משוחרר, hu u-beno ve-avdo meshuchrar, he and his son and his
freed slave. And this was when there was still a בית המקדש
Beis Hamikdash so they went to the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash to
testify. וקבלו הכהנים אותו ואת בנו, ve-kibbelu ha-kohanim oto ve-et bno, the
כהנים kohanim accepted him and his son ופסלו את עבדו, u-paslu et
avdo, they invalidated the slave, so presumably they ruled like רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon that relatives are good but they invalidated the freed slave.
Now why they had that hierarchy it's not clear but one does
wonder if it has a little bit to do with the fact
that they're כהנים, kohanim, so therefore as כהנים kohanim they're particularly sensitive
to the issues of hierarchy based on status and lineage also specifically
about lineage. So they were less concerned about the fact that they
were related and more concerned about the fact that this guy had
been a slave and they invalidated the slave. וכשבאו
לפני בית דין, u-keshe-bau lifnei beis din, when they came to the
בית דין beis din which was like the rabbis, again interesting how
the כהנים kohanim it's presumably happening in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash
or in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, the כהנים kohanim have the first say but
the rabbis have the final say, again that interesting question of
through whose lens do we understand who was running things at the
time of the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. בית דין קבלו אותו ואת
עבדו, beis din kibbelu oto ve-et avdo, I'm sorry, בית דין קבלו
אותו ואת עבדו beis din kibbelu oto ve-et avdo ופסלו את בנו,
u-paslu et beno, they accepted him and his slave and invalidated the
son. I mean I guess they could have invalidated him but the
point is they wouldn't accept him and his son, they're relatives, that
did matter. I mean I guess it did matter, they wouldn't accept
them both, but they didn't care about the fact that this guy
was a freed slave, now he's a Jew, lineage didn't matter. So
I think even like embedded in this already
you see a little bit, I mean there's a to me not
a so subtle subtext here about the difference of the rabbinic approach
and about the priestly approach. Right, for כהנים kohanim the whole כהונה
kehunah status is a status of אב ובנו. ab u-beno. That's the
whole כהונה kehunah status. How was that going to object to them?
What bothered them was this guy, he's a slave, he's a כנעני.
Kena'ani. Yeah, but now he's Jewish, now he's Jewish. So his slave
status was what bothered them. The rabbis, they weren't impressed with lineage
and with father and son, for them it was more this sort
of egalitarianism, not exactly that, but anyway certainly not the same degree
of hierarchy that comes from a כהונה kehunah type of an approach
and relatives is a problem and this being a freed slave is
not. David you had a question?
Yeah when a group came to testify after the court heard two
correct witnesses is that it?
Can they sanctify the moon? Yeah well we'll see about that. Okay.
אמר רב לוי, amar Rav Levi, מאי טעמא דרבי שמעון, mai ta'ama
de-Rabbi Shimon, what's the reason of רבי שמעון? Rabbi Shimon? דכתיב, de-chtiv,
that it says that relatives can be witnesses, we never heard that
before. דכתיב, de-chtiv, the verse says
ויאמר ה' אל משה ואל אהרן בארץ מצרים לאמר החודש הזה לכם.
va-yomer Hashem el Moshe ve-el Aharon be-eretz Mitzrayim lemor ha-chodesh ha-zeh lachem.
ניסן Nissan and B, the idea that there's a מצוה mitzvah to
sanctify the month based on the new moon. So it says לכם.
lachem. עדות זו תהא כשירה בכם, Edut zu tehi kesheira bachem, you
משה, Moshe, אהרן, Aharon, you could be witnesses together for the new
moon. So brothers can be witnesses. So relatives can be witnesses. רבנן,
Rabbanan, what do the רבנן Rabbanan say back? No, עדות זו תהא
מסורה לכם. Edut zu tehi mesura lachem. No, it means that this
is your responsibility, you the leaders of the generation, you know, it's
not something that gets done automatically, it's something as we know that
we have said and we'll say before, אתם אפילו שוגגים אתם אפילו
מזידים, atem afilu shogegim atem afilu mezidim, ultimately the calendar is fixed
by the religious leaders, and we play a role in accepting the
witnesses and in determining how the calendar will be fixed, or we
not only play a role, we actually make up the, you know,
we do the, we make those decisions. So that's what it means,
but not that brothers can be witnesses. Now the idea besides saying
that it's a פסוק pasuk that brothers can be witnesses, you know,
one of the ideas behind this is that what does it mean
to testify to sort of static facts as opposed to testify to
events? Like you know, in like American courts they think they have
something called like expert witnesses, right? So it's like conceptually a different
category. Like, yes, I looked at the blood, I did the matching
of the DNA, da da da. That's like called an expert witness,
but that's like a different category than I saw the guy take
out the gun and shoot him, right, which is like an eye
witness to the
events. What?
No?
Expert witness can be to an event.
I guess that's true, I guess that's a good point. If I
came along and I said not an event, but I said like,
yeah, I was passing by there and I saw some blood on
the scene. It wasn't an event, it's just a static fact, that
also
would be the same type of a witness. That's a good point.
That's a good point. But anyway, so but one does wonder here
if there you know, I'm trying to think in הלכה, halacha, right,
if somebody were just to come and say, you know, mostly testimony
you have is about this person, you know, did this type of
a violation, this type of an act. But,
yeah, well that's normally because we need to direct, but that I'm
wondering if that's based on the concept of what testimony is about,
or that's based on the concept that we tend not to interpret
facts. We're always interpreting in one way, but we tend to actually
sort of you know, like not make judgments based on circumstantial evidence.
So if we're not making decisions based on circumstantial evidence, you're always
going to need direct testimony. But that might not be so much
as conceptually that what I'm trying to get at is, is that
you know to what degree is the testifying on the new moon
classic testimony or if it's just testifying on like I saw a
fact rather than I saw somebody do something like an event? Because
that is rarer in הלכה, halacha, but the reason it might be
rarer might be because like I'm saying because normally we don't make
דין din based on circumstances. We need direct evidence. Yeah. So another
way I heard this once from רב Rav Lichtenstein was רב אהרן
Rav Aharon Lichtenstein was, I think it's more less than a question
of events versus facts as opposed to the פסוק pasuk says כי
יקום עד חמס באיש, ki yakum ed hamas b'ish, if a witness
rises up against a person, so to what degree classic testimony is
understood to be testifying against someone. So as opposed to this where
you're not testifying against someone, maybe it's not in the classic category
of testimony. So it is interesting this idea that it might be
something that you don't have the normal rules of who's כשר kasher
and who's invalid, that you can actually validate relatives. What did you
want to say though?
Maybe even it sounds from the way you're talking it's more it's
closer to the concept of
מומחה, mumcheh, like we saw that מומחה mumcheh we have that language
in other places in ש"ס. Shas. Yeah, so it sounds like they're
functioning more that way.
Yeah, but I've retracted, they're not really it's not really about experts,
but it is really more about like just saying a state of
affairs, we saw a moon rather than we saw an event. But
again, why that should put them in exactly a different category like
I said, רב Rav Lichtenstein once said the idea that it has
to be classic testimony is to testify against somebody. You know, I
guess in a way it also raises the whole issue about עד
אחד נאמן באיסורין, ed echad ne'eman b'issurin, right, if you sort of
say that this is like this piece of meat is כשר kosher
or טרף treif or whatever, you know, that's not classic testimony, there
you allow one witness, you allow women, you know, etc., so it's
also like more of like of a state of affairs or it's
certainly not against a person like to testify about you know, that
somebody else is sort of being the target of the testimony. All
right, so that's the idea here that it's possible that you can
have even relatives. אמר רבי יוסי, Amar Rabbi Yose, says אמר רבי
יוסי, Amar Rabbi Yose, מעשה בטוביה הרופא, Ma'aseh b'Tuvya Harofeh,
so the story here of טוביה Tuvya the doctor and his son
and the slave, freed slave. אמר רב חנן בר אבא, Amar Rav
Chanan bar Abba, הלכתא כרבי שמעון, hilchta k'Rabbi Shimon, we rule like
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that relatives can be witnesses. for עדות החודש.
edut hachodesh. אמר ליה רב הונא לרב חנה בר אבא, Amar lei
Rav Huna leRav Chana bar Abba, רבי יוסי ומעשה? Rabbi Yosi u'maaseh?
As רב הונא Rav Huna said to רב חנה, Rav Chana, one
minute,
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi says they can't and he gave a story
where they were rejected, the father and the son. רבי יוסי ומעשה.
Rabbi Yosi u'maaseh. ואת אמרת הלכתא כרבי שמעון? Ve'at amart hilcheta keRabbi
Shimon? And you're ruling like רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that says relatives
can be witnesses for קידוש החודש? kiddush hachodesh? אמר ליה, Amar lei,
so
then the response back was: Well, why shouldn't I be able to
say that? דזימנין סגיאין אמרית קמיה דרב, De'zimnin sagi'in amrit kamei de'Rav,
many times I said in the presence of רב, Rav, הלכתא כרבי
שמעון, hilcheta keRabbi Shimon, that we rule like רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
in this משנה, mishnah, ולא אמר לי ולא מידי, v'lo amar li
v'lo midi, and he didn't respond anything to me, so clearly I'm
right. אמר ליה, Amar lei, so he said back to him, one
minute. היכי תנית? Heichi tanit? How did you teach it in front
of רב? Rav? Who did you, what did you say רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon say and what did you say רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi
say? אמר ליה איפכא. Amar lei ipcha. So he said to him
the reverse of what we have in our משנה. mishnah. So yeah,
I said the הלכה halacha like רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon because I
said רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon was the one who disqualified relatives. אמר
ליה משום הכי לא אמר לך ולא מידי. Amar lei mishum hachi
lo amar lach v'lo midi.
That's why he didn't contradict you because you were telling him that
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon said it's invalid and fine, then he's okay
to rule like
רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. אמר טבי ברי דמרי טבי
אמר מר עוקבא אמר שמואל. Amar Tavi brei de'Mari Tavi amar Mar
Ukva amar Shmuel. So now here we have this whole lineage saying
in the name of שמואל, Shmuel, הלכתא כרבי שמעון. hilcheta keRabbi Shimon.
We rule like רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. Now the question is: Which
version of רבי שמעון? Rabbi Shimon? The רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that
says it's valid or the רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that says it's
invalid? And you'll notice at the side that some people sneak in
one word here
in the ספר אחר: sefer acher: אין הלכתא כרבי שמעון.
Ein hilcheta keRabbi Shimon. Now that seems to be clearly a later
gloss because it wouldn't say אין, ein, it would say לית. leit.
לית הלכתא כרבי שמעון. Leit hilcheta keRabbi Shimon. But anyway, so it's
quite interesting. So in the end how did we end up? What
does the גמרא gemara say and anyway which version of the positions
did they have? The general assumption is that עדות החודש edut hachodesh
is not valid with relatives, but the final decision remains, and certainly
that's the פשט peshat of the גמרא, gemara, the story validated the
idea that you would not accept relatives, but the final conclusion remains
murky. Let's just finish till the end here of the פרק perek
and then I'll take some questions. So: אלו הן הפסולין, Elu hen
hapsulin, the following are invalid. המשחק בקוביא ומלוה ברבית, Hamisachek bakuvya umalveh
beribbit, this is the famous משנה mishnah from סנהדרין. Sanhedrin. People who
play dice and lend money in interest, ומפריחי יונים umafrichei yonim who
race pigeons, וסוחרי שביעית vesocharei shevi'it and do business with שביעית shevi'it
produce, make business off of it when you're not supposed to profit,
ועבדים ve'avadim
and slaves. And women goes without saying, as we're going to see.
זה הכלל, Ze haklal, this is the rule: כל עדות שאין האשה
כשרה לה אף הן אינן כשרים לה. Kol edut she'ein ha'ishah kesherah
lah af hen einan kesherim lah. Any testimony that a woman is
not כשרה kesherah for, even they are not כשרים kesherim for. Which
by the way תוספות Tosafot points out, part of the point here
is that even according to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon or whoever it
was that said relatives are כשר, kasher, relatives are כשר kasher because
there each person individually is a כשר kasher witness. The only problem
is they're coming together. So that's okay. But these people that are
individually invalid, either because of sin or because of a slave or
because of a woman, as even taken singly they're invalid, everybody agrees
that they remain invalid for קידוש החודש. kiddush hachodesh. Now what does
it mean: אין האשה כשרה לה? ein ha'ishah kesherah lah? Which testimony
is a woman כשרה kesherah for? So the testimony a woman is
כשרה kesherah for is to testify that a woman's husband died. Okay,
that we know at the end of יבמות, Yevamot, also something actually
relating to סוטה Sotah which is this week's פרשה, parsha, but primarily
to testify that a woman's husband died. That a woman can testify
for, that the רבנים rabbanim gave a lot of latitude, that even
allows hearsay testimony, עד מפי עד. ed mipi ed. So for that
as well, these types of people would be כשר kasher for that,
but not for something that is a classic formal testimony that women
are invalid, then everybody here is invalid as well. What does the
גמרא gemara say about this? גמרא האשה כשרה לה אף הן כשרים
לה. Gemara: ha'ishah kesherah lah af hen kesherim lah. So in cases
where women would be good, these would all be good as well.
So that's: אמר רב אשי, Amar Rav Ashi, says רב אשי, Rav
Ashi, זאת אומרת, zot omeret, this teaches you, גזלן דדבריהם, gazlan de'divreihem,
that a rabbinic גזלן, gazlan, because that's what most of these people
in this category are considered, I'll unpack that in a minute, כשרים
לעדות
אשה kesherim le'edut ishah are כשר kasher for testimony related to allow
a woman to get remarried. So that's the classic example of testimony
that a woman can testify about is עדות אשה, edut ishah, meaning
the אשה ishah here does not mean the testify-er but means the
object of the testimony, to testify about a woman that she can
remarry. But those, that testimony that a woman's husband has died, you
allow a woman and therefore
hearsay, and you allow all of these people as long as you
are not a biblical גזלן, gazlan, as long as you're only a
rabbinic גזלן. gazlan. Now what does it mean that everybody here is
only a rabbinic גזלן? gazlan? First of all, the first thing you
have to appreciate is that the two categories of why people are
invalid to testify. One is because of the type of sin, the
severity of the sin, which is called a, you know, a... חייבי
מלכות chayavei malkus
based on the פסוק pasuk אם בן הכות הרשע, im bin hakkos
harasha, if the wicked person is deserving of lashes. So we see
that somebody deserving of lashes is considered a רשע. rasha. And the
פסוק pasuk says אל תשת רשע עד, al tashes rasha eid, a
רשע rasha can't testify. So therefore any sin that's deserving of lashes
invalidates the person, even if it's not really relevant to the testimony.
So what if, I don't know, this guy, you know, ate on
יום כיפור? Yom Kippur? What does that have to do with trusting
him about something else? But nevertheless, that makes him by status a
רשע rasha and invalidates him. That's not what we're talking about. We're
talking about אם בן הכות הרשע. im bin hakkos harasha. We're talking
about another
another concept which is called רשע דחמס. rasha dechamas. Somebody who's a
רשע rasha because of a monetary sin, which is based on the
פסוק pasuk of אל תשת ידך עם רשע להיות עד חמס. al
tashes yadecha im rasha lihyos eid chamas. And there the concern is
not about the severity of the sin so much as about the
fact that he can be bought. He's got a price. He's willing
to sin because of monetary gain, and therefore his testimony is considered
to be up for sale and therefore you cannot trust it. That's
the focus of this משנה. mishna. So this משנה mishna though says
that the people listed here are considered גזלן דבריהם. gazlan d'divreihem. It's
only rabbinic. Why is it only rabbinic? Some of this sounds biblical.
Well, okay. The guy that's racing pigeons and playing dice, that maybe
like it's a little shady and you're maybe taking money that you
didn't really earn and the גמרא Gemara has all these questions about
אסמכתא קניא, asmachta kanya, is the bet that you made really legally
binding or not and if it's not really legally binding then the
guy's paying you money he didn't really owe you. Okay, but that's
still, you understand, it's not out-and-out theft, you know, it's not an
out-and-out type of a of a biblical violation. But how about something
like lending money with interest, right, or doing business with פירות שביעית?
peiros sheviis? That seems to be a biblical issue. So תוספות Tosafos
tries to explain it in two ways and רש"י Rashi in a
third. The two ways תוספות Tosafos explains it is either that we're
talking about certain types of interest and certain types of business with
פירות שביעית peiros sheviis that are only rabbinic violations. There are those,
there are those different categories. Or that a person doesn't really like
rationalizes and doesn't really know that the things that they're doing is
really a biblical violation. And if they themselves not aware that what
they're doing is a biblical violation, then you know, look, I can
rationalize. Yeah, what I'm doing it wasn't so bad or whatever, which
means that if I really was something that I really wouldn't be
able to rationalize, I really would understand it's a really bad violation,
I wouldn't do it. So it doesn't make me a clear clearly
prepared to violate regardless. That's how תוספות Tosafos explains it. So it's
not really that it's rabbinic but maybe like I think it's rabbinic.
I like downplay the severity, I'm able to just to rationalize in
my head why it's not an out-and-out violation. רש"י Rashi says a
little bit differently. רש"י Rashi says that the issue here is is
that even if, and this is important, it is a biblical violation,
it's still not out-and-out theft. Meaning, it's not like I stole money
from you. Like you know if I see a Coke lying around,
I don't know whose it is, okay, it's a Coke, what difference
does it make? I'm sure you know I take it, whatever. Technically
maybe that's also the rationalizing part. But the point for רש"י Rashi
is that if I'm really doing if I'm not actually going and
stealing something from you, then it's not for people in their mindset
how bad it is, it's not just questioning is it biblical, is
it rabbinic. It's like, you know, the nature of the whole interaction.
And therefore since these things are not out-and-out theft, that doesn't mean
that I'd be prepared to do things, you know, that are like
you know that are like really like put my testimony up for
sale. Only if I'm really going to go and do out-and-out theft
will will that undermine the trustworthiness of my testimony. So these are
these gray categories and therefore you cannot accept them for standard testimony
but you can accept them for testifying that a woman's husband has
died. The only case that you can't accept testimony for a woman's
husband has died is somebody who's like an out-and-out גזלן. gazlan. That
type of person, his testimony's up for sale and you can't trust
him you know even in something that the rabbis gave you a
lot of latitude for. Yes?
So for two things, at the end of the last סוגיא sugya
it was just striking in terms of the editing of the גמרא
Gemara that טבי בר אבא Tavi bar Abba ומר טבי, veMar Tavi,
first of all you had טוביה הרופא Tuvya Harofei and also you
had
טבי העבד Tavi Ha'eved
and you had to have that same exact...
That's a good point. I was thinking about טבי העבד Tavi Ha'eved
but I didn't I wasn't also thinking about you're right, it's טוביה
הרופא. Tuvya Harofei. There's a lot of טביs Tavi going around there.
That's a good point.
Also in terms of women's being פסולי עדות, psulei eidus, so is
it that they fall into they're assumed to fall into one of
these two categories in the paradigm or is there a פסוק pasuk
there's a third reason why they're פסולי
עדות
psulei
eidus like intrinsically? Like women are presumed to be buyable per you
know in other words like they fall into the paradigm of רשע
דחמס? rasha dechamas?
No, no, no. Women are invalid just because it says אנשים, anashim,
אנשים ולא נשים. anashim velo nashim. Right, that's what I'm saying. So
it's a third... Yeah, yeah, right, it's true. It's like it's not
such a pleasant grouping, you know, גזלנים gazlanim and slaves and women.
Right, but and they're for different reasons, but it's funny how like
the women issue is the determinant of the whole category. Let's finish
this up. מי שראה החודש Mi shera'ah hachodesh ואינו יכול להלך, lehalech,
להלוך, lehaloch, לילך. leilech. Wouldn't we say לילך? leilech? Anyway,
להלך. lehalech. להלך, lehalech, yeah, sounds fine. Anyway, ואינו יכול להלך, ve'eino
yachol lehalech, מוליכין אותו על החמור. molichin oto al hachamor. So somebody
saw it and again it's שבת Shabbat and they can't walk, so
you put them on a donkey. Again you can violate שבת Shabbat
if necessary. אפילו במיטה, Afilu bemitah, even if you have to put
his bed on the donkey, you know, to keep him, to keep
him
healthy or whatever, you know, he can't manage a normal trip sitting
straight up. ואם צודה להם, Ve'im tzodah lahem, if people are laying
in wait to waylay them, לוקחין בידם מקלות, lokchin beyadam maklot, they
can take weapons, sticks. ואם היתה דרך רחוקה, Ve'im hayetah derech rechokah,
and if it was a long journey, לוקחין בידם מזונות, lokchin beyadam
mezonot, they can take food. So they can do whatever they need
even though it's all on שבת Shabbat and they're doing this. שמהלך
לילה ויום מחללין עליו את השבת, Shemahalach laylah vayom mechalelin alav et
haShabbat, if you can get there through the night and the next
day before, right, because if you get there a day late it's
not going to do any good. You've got to get there the
same day that it's ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh in order for you
to be able your testimony to be effective. But if you can,
if it's within a night and a day's journey, so you can
get there before the following nightfall, you can violate שבת Shabbat ויוצאים
להעיד על החודש veyotzim leha'id al hachodesh and go to testify on
the new moon, שנאמר אלה מועדי השם אשר תקראו אותם במועדם, shenemar
eleh mo'adei Hashem asher tikre'u otam bemo'adam, these are the holidays of
God that you will declare them in their right time. So במועדם
bemo'adam even on שבת. Shabbat. Now the issue הדרן עלך ארבעה ראשי
שנים, Hadran alach arba'ah rashei shanim, so that's the end of that
and of course we continue without any break, not just because it's
the דף daf but because the next משנה Mishna just continues exactly
the previous. So it's very funny sometimes where the פרקים prakim are
divided. Okay, but we are going to see in the next משנה
Mishna what this idea would be that there are people waiting to
waylay them. Why would you waylay somebody? I mean it's שבת, Shabbat,
they won't necessarily have money on them, maybe you want to get
their horses, but we're going to see that one of the reasons
will be because of the sectarians that try to interfere with the
normal process of קידוש החודש. Kiddush Hachodesh. So let's take a look
now at the next משנה. Mishna. אם אינן מכירין אותו, Im einan
makirin oto, let's say the בית דין Beit Din doesn't recognize who
these witnesses are. So and maybe these witnesses, as we're going to
see, are sectarians who are trying to make trouble. So what will
they do? משלחים עמו אחר להעידו, meshalchin imo acher leha'ido, the town
that he is being sent from, they'll send another person along with
him that the בית דין Beit Din does recognize, and that person
can give like a, not character reference, but you know, whatever, can
testify like, yes, you know me, you know I'm trustworthy, I'm telling
you that he's a good guy too, he's trustworthy, he's not one
of those sectarians that's coming to mess everything up. And now we're
going to give you a little context, historical context. בראשונה, Barishonah, well
it's a little different, but okay, but anyway close enough. בראשונה היו
מקבלין עדות החודש מכל אדם, Barishonah hayu mekabelin edut hachodesh mikol adam,
originally, what did they care if they knew somebody? Anybody who walked
in their doors they'd accept the testimony of the new moon. משקלקלו
הבייתוסים, Mishekilkelu haBaitusim, which is quite interesting, often we have צדוקים, Tzadokim,
בייתוסים Baitusim to be the ones in particular, well specifically identified as
the בייתוסים Baitusim as the particular sect that is behind it is
interesting. Anyway, when the בייתוסים Baitusim ruined things, they started interfering, התקינו
שלא יהיו מקבלין אלא מן המכירין, hitkinu shelo yehu mekabelin ela min
hamakirin, they would only accept testimony from people they recognized or from
people that they recognized who could, you know, speak on behalf of
somebody else. And the reason is as you know very interesting, we're
coming up to שבועות, Shavuot, it's all about שבועות. Shavuot. You start
counting the fifty days ממחרת השבת mimmachorat haShabbat from the day after
פסח Pesach or from the day after the שבת Shabbat after פסח.
Pesach. And since the בייתוסים Baitusim wanted the calendar to be based
on fifty days from Sunday, not fifty days from the sixteenth of
ניסן, Nisan, they would try to manipulate the calendar so that it
would work out, so that the calendar that the rabbis were setting
would actually work for them. Now it's a little interesting because you
know some things we know about like the Jubilee, the people that
wrote the Book of Jubilees and the other people that did these
that had these various sects, they didn't deal with the rabbinic calendar,
they just made their own calendar. But presumably, right, okay, you guys
do this, we're doing something else. But presumably there were these בייתוסים
Baitusim who wanted actually to, you know,
have everybody's calendar work with theirs. Maybe they didn't want to be
so sectarian, they wanted to just force it that everybody was doing
their understanding of how it should be, so they tried to get
testimony to be so it would work out that פסח Pesach would
be on שבת. Shabbat. And if פסח Pesach would be on שבת,
Shabbat, then the calendars would coincide. The day after פסח Pesach would
also be the day after שבת. Shabbat. They tried to manipulate it
and therefore the rabbis wanted to make sure they were only getting
testimony from people that they could trust. Yes.
This indicates to a certain lack of confidence in the דרישה וחקירה,
drishah vachakirah, right? Like what are they asking them all the questions
for about the
moon if they if they thought
they could be befuddled.
But you know, if if somebody knows astronomy well enough, you prep
somebody well enough, right, right, it's true. I mean, is it the
דרישה וחקירה drishah vachakirah to make sure that you're not intentionally lying
or is it the דרישה וחקירה drishah vachakirah to make sure you're
not mistaken? Right. So you know, I assumed it was more to
make sure you're not mistaken, but right. So let's take a look.
But you also
remember they wanted to manipulate, right? They sent to intimidate them, right?
So it takes so it could be... You can try to, "Are
you sure it's this?" and then you start asking all these questions,
"Oh, I don't know, maybe."
Precisely, it's a way, right, of
if you don't want to go with what they have to say.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says מאי אחר? mai acher? What does
it mean they send somebody else to testify, to be a character
witness? חד, chad, only one other person. So the גמרא Gemara says
וחד מי מהימן? v'chad mi meheman? Since when do you trust one
person? Now, of course, they're making up the rules here, you know,
they're deciding they need character witnesses, so although normally you'd need two,
maybe they would be happy with one. But let's take a reason
why it seems like, why one would not be enough. והתניא, v'hatanya,
מיתנא ברייתא, mi-tna braita, מעשה שבא הוא ועדיו עמו להעיד עליה. maaseh
sheba hu v'adav imo l'haid aleha.
There's a story where a certain person came with his witnesses to
testify about him. So you needed two witnesses. So how come this
suggests that you only need one witness? So אמר פפא, amar Pappa,
מאי אחד זוג אחד? mai echad zug echad? זוג אחר, zug acher,
what does it mean? זוג אחר, zug acher, it means he sent
another pair, not one person, you need two people to testify. הכי
נמי מסתברא, hachi nami mistabra, you know what? That makes sense. אי
אמרת בשלמא הכי, ei amrat bishlama hachi, if they don't recognize אותו,
oso, if it says they don't recognize him, they have to send
somebody else to validate, you know, for him,
so מאי אותו? mai oso? What does it mean they don't recognize
him? אילימא אותו חד, eileima oso chad, they don't, it's one guy
they're sending and the בית דין Beis Din doesn't recognize him, חד
מי מהימן? chad mi meheman? One guy wouldn't be enough. משפט כתיב
ביה, mishpat kesiv bei, it says, you know, משפט לאלוהי יעקב, mishpat
l'Elohei Yaakov, the testimony of the new moon is like a normal
court case, you need two witnesses. אלא מאי אותו, ela mai oso,
so when it says the town is sending him, it doesn't mean
they're only sending one guy, אותו הזוג, oso hazug, it means they're
sending a pair. So the singular refers to a pair. הכי נמי
מאי אחר, hachi nami mai acher, so when it says they send
another to testify on his behalf, what does another mean? זוג אחר,
zug acher, it means another pair. Now that's a pretty bad proof,
as תוספות Tosafos says, because since when can the town not send
one person? We just learned before, you know, you send thousands of
people are going, you don't know who's going to work out. Or
maybe תוספות Tosafos says maybe the town is sending a pair and
of that pair there's one guy that isn't recognized, you know, so
but actually then the other guy could probably testify. Anyway, the point
is, it's not so clear why we have to assume that the
town is sending two. But that's what the גמרא Gemara says, presumably
the town is sending two, so אותו oso means the pair. So
when it says they send someone else to testify, it doesn't mean
a single person is being the character witness, it means two people
are being character witnesses. Again, a pretty forced reading of the משנה,
Mishnah, the משנה Mishnah sounds like one is enough. Let's keep on
going.
Yes, but the one is a character witness. Right. Are they testifying
to the moon or just to the character? Right. Right, so that's
why the גמרא, Gemara,
the idea that you need two character witnesses is not based on
the פסוק. pasuk. The idea that normal עדות eidus means two. Because
why would you need one witness for a character witness? You would
think. And that's what the משנה Mishnah seems to say. But since
the גמרא Gemara has a ברייתא braita that says two witnesses, so
it wants to get the משנה Mishnah to work with the ברייתא.
braita. So to get the משנה Mishnah to work with the ברייתא,
braita, it reinterprets the משנה Mishnah to say two character witnesses. But
I agree with you, it seems to definitely be a forced reading
of the משנה. Mishnah. And the גמרא's Gemara not dumb. Let's take
a look. The גמרא Gemara says וחד לא מהימן? v'chad lo meheman?
Are you telling me that one is not believed as a character
witness? והתניא, v'hatanya, מיתנא ברייתא, mi-tna braita, מעשה ברבי נהוראי, maaseh b'Rabbi
Nehorai, a story with Rabbi Nehorai, שהלך אצל העד להעיד עליו, shehalach
eitzel ha'eid l'haid alav, he went to testify to be a character
witness for a particular witness. בשבת לאושא. b'Shabbos l'Usha. Now look at
this, this is important. Not only can the witness violate שבת, Shabbos,
the character witness can violate שבת, Shabbos, obviously, because if the witness
won't be accepted, then he's not doing any good. So this is
the same way you can send a donkey and provisions, you can
send a character witness. That's what you need in order to get
this guy to testify. So Rabbi Nehorai went on שבת Shabbos to
be a character witness for another witness. So you see, it's only
one guy, only one character witness, not two. So the גמרא Gemara
says, no, אמרי, amri, you can say, רבי נהוראי סהדא אחרינא הוה
בהדיה. Rabbi Nehorai sahada achrina hava behadeih. Rabbi Nehorai wasn't alone, there
was another guy with him, there were two character witnesses. וחד דלא
חשיב ליה, v'chad d'lo chashiv leih,
why didn't it mention the other guy? Why does it only mention
Rabbi Nehorai? שבקוה לרבי נהוראי shabuk Rav Nehorai because who cares about
the other guy? Some Joe Shmoe, we're not going to mention
him. The חידוש chiddush is even Rabbi Nehorai would violate שבת Shabbos
just to be a character witness, okay? So we want to underscore
that. Yeah, but there were two character witnesses, fine. So again, the
simple sense of the משנה, Mishnah, the simple sense of this ברייתא
braita is that one character witness, but the גמרא's Gemara reading it
to say two.
The whole point is that you need two, the whole point is
that Joe Shmoe is the important guy, he's the second guy.
Right. Okay, but even Rabbi Nehorai would be violating שבת, Shabbos, it's
one thing that Joe Shmoe would violate שבת. Shabbos. Okay, רב אשי
אמר, Rav Ashi amar, Rav Ashi said, רבי נהוראי סהדא אחרינא הוה
באושא, Rabbi Nehorai sahada achrina hava b'Usha, ואזל
רבי נהוראי לאצטרופי בהדיה. v'azal Rabbi Nehorai l'itztarufi behadeih. No, no, no.
First of all, the whole story is wrong. Rabbi Nehorai was, it
wasn't that somebody else went with him, there was another witness already
there in אושא. Usha. So the other guy didn't have to violate
שבת. Shabbos. The only person that had to violate שבת Shabbos was
Rabbi Nehorai. Yes, you needed two character witnesses or he could, you
read this גמרא Gemara that they were both actually there.
Yes, but but
anyway, yes you needed two either way, but only one of them,
only רב נוראי Rav Norai had to violate שבת. Shabbat. So the
גמרא Gemara says אי הכי מאי למימרא? Ee hachi mai l'meimra? Now
the גמרא Gemara says: so what's the whole חידוש chiddush of all
of this? מהו דתימא מספיקא לא מחללינן שבתא, Mahu d'teima masfeika lo
m'chal'linan Shabtasa,
I might have thought that out of a doubt because רש"י Rashi
says look, if I go with another witness, if if either only
I alone am needed or I'm going together with the other witness,
we know that we're both going to be there, we're both going
to be doing our job. But if I'm going and I need
another guy and I don't even know if the other guy's around,
like I'm assuming that the other character witness is in the town,
but for all I know he's left for the country for שבת.
Shabbat. So maybe that's not a good enough reason for me to
violate שבת. Shabbat. קא משמע לן Ka mashma lan that I should
do it anyway. Now of course you could say that's true about
a lot of these cases, right? A hundred people saw and I'm
going, they might not need me. But there, I definitely saw and
my testimony definitely could be like accepted. Here maybe you'll figure look,
A, I didn't see, I'm only a character witness, B, I might
not be a good enough character witness if the other guy isn't
there. And nevertheless, even though רב נוראי Rav Norai went alone, even
that רב נוראי Rav Norai went alone because he he was relying
on the other guy being there. Okay, so that's how we're reading
the case, but the upshot of all of this is is that
against the simple reading of the משנה Mishnah we're asserting that you
need two character witnesses. Okay. כי
אתא עולא, He'asa Ulla, when עולא Ulla came from ארץ ישראל, Eretz
Yisrael, אמר amar כי קדשוהו לירחא במערבא. ki kiddshu lei yarcha b'ma'arava.
Remember we had this before, this might even be the same case.
עולא Ulla comes from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and tells us oh,
they, you know, they sanctified the new moon in ארץ ישראל. Eretz
Yisrael. So אמר רב כהנא, amar Rav Kahana, now again, this is
not like he's telling us oh, we're celebrating יום כיפור Yom Kippur
on the wrong day. יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, right. He's just whatever
he's telling us, he's telling us when they sanctified the new moon
in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. So can we trust a somebody who
just comes and testifies what happened in ארץ ישראל? Eretz Yisrael? What
do you need to trust now, not the witness in a way
to trust the שליח, shaliach, as it were, to trust the person
that's delivering the report of what happened in ארץ ישראל? Eretz Yisrael?
So אמר רב כהנא: amar Rav Kahana: לא מיבעיא עולא, lo mibaya
Ulla, goes without saying that we can trust עולא, Ulla, דגברא רבא
הוא, d'gavra raba hu, he's a great person, he's a big rabbi,
very obviously we could trust him, דהימן, de'hemen, of course we could
trust him. אלא אפילו איניש דעלמא נמי מהימן, Ella afilu inish d'alma
nami m'heiman, and even some normal Joe Schmo again, even some normal
Joe Schmo we would trust. Now this is in contrast to the
witness. Who can we trust as a witness? That has to be
somebody that we know, somebody we can trust. Who can we trust
as a reporter of what happened? That we can trust anyone. Why?
I mean if people wanted to interfere they can interfere whether at
the testimony end or at the reporting end. No, here's why it's
different. מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? כל מילתא דעבידא לאגלויי לא משקרי בה
אינשי. Kol milta d'avida l'igluyi lo m'shakri bei inshay.
Anything that's a lie will be revealed, people don't lie. You know,
I don't know, you know, nowadays with the blogosphere or whatever, I
mean you can spread a lot of things that ultimately aren't true
and you can change a lot of impressions. Okay, but anyway, nevertheless
the גמרא Gemara says that we're going to have higher standards, we're
going to need to know who's saying it in terms of accepting
the testimony. In terms of can we believe a report if we're
in the גולה, golah, that we will believe anyone because eventually the
word will get out regardless.
Just like מגולה. m'golah. Right. תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami hachi, we've
taught similarly, בא
אחד בסוף העולם ואמר קדשו בית דין את החודש נאמן. ba echad
b'sof olam v'amar kiddshu beit din et hachodesh ne'eman.
So we will trust anyone to say what happened because that will
be, that will be ultimately that'll become well known. We won't necessarily
trust people to testify on the new moon unless we know who
they are. Okay, now we have to have the story about the
ביתוסים, Baitusim, a very humorous גמרא Gemara coming up. Okay, בראשונה היו
מקבלין עדות החודש מכל אדם. barishona hayu m'kablin edut hachodesh mikol adam.
Originally they used to accept this from anyone. So says until the
ביתוסים Baitusim started interfering. So תנו רבנן, tana rabanan, we taught in
a ברייתא, baraita, מה קלקול קלקלו הבייתוסים, mah kilkul kilkulu ha'baitusim, what
did they do to to make things to ruin things? פעם אחת
בקשו ביתוסים להטעות את החכמים, pa'am achat bikshu baitusim l'hat'ot et hachachamim,
once they wanted to to, you know, to
make the rabbis err, to deceive the rabbis in terms of when
was ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh. שכרו שני בני אדם בארבע מאות זוז,
sachru shnei b'nei adam b'arba meot zuz, they hired two people with
four hundred זוז zuz to give back to give false testimony on
when they saw the new moon. אחד משלנו, echad mishelanu,
one of them was actually a rabbinic Jew, they didn't know it
but he was one of ours, he was one of, you know,
he's on our team. ואחד משלהם, v'echad mishelahem, and one of them
was from theirs, but they didn't realize that the first guy they
hired is undercover. I don't know if he was undercover, it doesn't
sound like he was undercover, it sounds like it happened to be
his sympathies were with the rabbis. Okay, let's take a look. משלהם
העיד עדותו ויצא, mishelahem he'id eduto v'yatza, so their man came, gave
his testimony, passed muster, left. משלנו, mishelanu, our guy, we didn't realize
he was our guy, the guy walked in, ואמרו לו, v'amru lo,
so they said to him, אמור כיצד ראית את הלבנה, emor keitzad
ra'ita et halevana, tell us how you saw the new moon. אמר
להם, amar lahem, he said to the people sort of, you know,
there cross-examining him, עולה הייתי במעלה אדומים, olei hayiti b'ma'aleh adumim, I
was going up in מעלה אדומים, Ma'aleh Adumim, וראיתי שהוא רבוץ בין
שני סלעים, v'ra'iti shehu ravutz bein shnei sla'im, I saw the moon,
it was crouching between two rocks, ראשו דומה לעגל, rosho domeh l'egel,
the head looked like a calf. אזניו דומים לגדי, oznav domim legadi,
the ears looked like a goat, קרניו דומות לצבי, karnav domos letzvi,
the horns of the of the moon looked like a look like
a deer, וזנבו מונחת לו בין ירכותיו, veznavo munachas lo bein yarchosav,
its tail was between its thighs, ונרתעתי, venirtati, and I peered closely
at it ונרתעתי, venirtati, and I was like I was like astounded,
you know, I was yeah, I trembled, right, I recoiled, ונפלתי לאחורי,
venafalti leachorai,
and I fell backwards, ואם אין אתם מאמינים לי, veim ein atem
ma'aminim li, and if you don't believe this fabulous story that I've
just told you, הרי מאתיים זוז צרורים לי בסדיני, harei masayim zuz
tzerurim li besidini, look, here's 200 zuz that I have in my
pocket that I was paid to tell the story so that you'll
believe me. So אמרו לו, amru lo, so they said to him,
מי שכרוך לכך, mi secharacha lekach, who got you to do this?
So אמר להם, amar lahem, he said to them, or like what
made you play along maybe is more what they're asking. So אמר
להם, amar lahem, he said to them, שמעתי שביתוסין מבקשים להטעות את
חכמים, shamati shebeitosin mevakshim lehatos es chachamim, I heard that the ביתוסין,
beitosin, I heard that they had this plot and they were trying
to, you know, to deceive you. אמרתי, amarti, and I said to
myself, אלך אני ואודיע להם, elech ani veodia lahem, let me go,
seem to be complicit in this, and I'll let the rabbis know
what's up, שמא יבואו בני אדם שאינם הגונים, shema yavo'u benei adam
sheeinam hagunim, because somebody else will come that really will buy into
their whole plot, ויטעו את חכמים, veyatu es chachamim, and they'll deceive
you. So אמרו לו, amru lo, so they said to him, מאתיים
זוז נתונים לך במתנה, masayim zuz netunim lecha bematana,
keep the 200 zuz, thank you very much, והשוכרך ימתח על העמוד,
vehasochercha yimatach al ha'amud,
and the guy that hired you, we're going to put him on
the, you know, on the pole and we're going to give him
the lashes. ובאותה שעה התקינו שלא יהו מקבלים אלא מן
המכירים. uveosa sha'ah hikinu shelo yehu mekabelim ela min hamakirim. From that
time on, they said we better know who it is that we're
getting this testimony from. You got to wonder, it's such a hilarious
story, Serpico. What?
Serpico story. Right, Serpico, sorry.
The
undercover agent in the New York City police department.
Okay. Anyway, but you got to wonder like why he told such
a fabulous story, like and why, what's the symbolism of? I didn't
have a chance to check, I'm sure the המהרש''א Maharsha says something
interesting about the symbolism of all of that.
Okay. Is this the language, by the way, of the corporal punishment,
ימתח על העמוד? yimatach al ha'amud?
Yes, yes, because a classic, yeah,
because somebody would be like, you know, on a whipping pole, like
there'd be a whipping pole or whatever, yeah, stretch them out. Okay,
let's just read the next משנה. Mishnah. בראשונה, Barishona, originally, היו משיאין
משואות, hayu masi'in masu'os,
they would, to communicate when ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh would be, they
would do it with bonfires. They would wave, you know, from one
mountaintop to another, you know, and then, you know, you can get
a message across very, very quickly if you have people on mountaintops,
you know, you can travel hundreds of miles by just doing like
a, you know, you see one guy's fire and you light your
fire and it's a daisy chain, you know, all the way for
hundreds of miles. So that's how they used to communicate that it
was ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh. משקלקלו הכותים, mishekilelu hakusim, now here it's
כותים, kusim, again, I didn't check the manuscript if this also is
ביתוסין. beitosin. Does somebody have Soncino? What does, I mean, what's his
name, Steinsaltz? What does Steinsaltz have? He has כותים kusim here.
ביתוסין, beitosin, yes. I don't know why it would change here. The
other one, it makes sense, it's the same ביתוסין beitosin that are
making a problem. כותים kusim anyway, just have their own calendar, they
weren't trying to influence the rabbinic calendar. Okay, so משקלקלו הכותים, mishekilelu
hakusim, on the wrong place? He has כותים. kusim.
Oh, he does, oh, he does have כותים kusim here.
So that's strange, like why all of a sudden here is it
the כותים kusim making problems rather than the ביתוסין. beitosin. Anyway, but
this is also very interesting, right? As opposed to what we just
said earlier in the גמרא, Gemara, that you are more willing to
believe people that communicate a message because it'll get figured out anyway,
here we're saying that where they interfered was not in the testimony,
but in the communication of the fact. Okay, of course here it's
better because it's one thing if you come personally and testify, then
you're putting your reputation on the line and then you can say
everybody's going to find out, then I'm not, I'm not going to
lie. But if all you do is you start going to mountaintops
and waving fires, it's anonymous. Nobody knows, you know, nobody knows that
you're doing it. So there, maybe you'll do it and even if
the facts will get revealed later on. Okay, so here there was
a problem not only in the, what do you call it, not
only in the testimony, but in the communication of it. So they
used to light fires, but then other people would interfere and light
fires at the wrong times. התקינו שיהו שלוחים יוצאים, hikinu sheyehu sheluchim
yotzim, so that finally led to sending out messengers. And with messengers,
somebody's putting their reputation on the line and, you know, you might
actually know who the messenger is, as we saw in the early
גמרא, Gemara, maybe even if you don't know who the messenger is,
but at least the person is putting his reputation on the line.
כיצד היו משיאין משואות? keitzad hayu masi'in masu'os? How did they light
the fires? מביאים כלונסאות של ארז ארוכים, mevi'im kelonsa'os shel erez aruchim,
they would take cedar poles, long poles, וקנים ועצי שמן ונעורת של
פשתן, ukanim va'atzei shemen veneores shel pishtan, and they would take all
these various flammable materials of twigs and olive wood and flax, וכורך
במשיחה, vekorech bimshicha, they would wrap it like into, like, you know,
some ball at the top
with a rope. They go to the top of the mountain ומצית
בהן את האור, umatzit bahen et ha-or, they'd light the fire ומוליך
ומביא ומעלה ומוריד, umolik u-mevi u-ma'ale u-morid, they go up and down
and side and back and forth. תוספות Tosafot said that that's in
order that you shouldn't think it's like a shooting star or something,
so those movements make it clear what it is. עד שרואה חברו
שהוא עושה כן בראש ההר השני, ad she-ro'eh havero she-hu oseh khen
be-rosh ha-har ha-sheni,
until you see that the guy at the other mountain who is
also כן ken in בראש ההר השני be-rosh ha-har ha-sheni is doing
the same thing, then you know that your message got across to
the next mountain and then so on and so forth until it
gets, you know, going mountain top to mountain top. וכן בראש ההר
השלישי, vekhen be-rosh ha-har ha-shlishi,
and similar to the third mountain and on and on. ומהיכן היו
משיאין משואות, ume-ayyin hayu masi'in masu'ot,
where would they start this from? מהר המשחה, me-har ha-mishha,
from הר הזיתים, Har Ha-Zeitim, from Mount of Olives. לסרטבא, le-Sartaba, that
would go
to
Sartaba, ומסרטבא לגרופינא, umi-Sartaba le-Grofina, ומגרופינא לחוורן, umi-Grofina le-Havran, ומחוורן לבית בלתין,
umi-Havran le-Beit Baltin, ומבית בלתין לא זזו משם. umi-Beit Baltin lo zazu
misham. בית בלתין Beit Baltin would be at some end of this
chain and they didn't stop
עד שרואה כל הגולה לפניו כמדורת אש, ad she-ro'eh kol ha-golah lefanav
kemadurat esh, from where the entire exile was like lit up by
a fire, all the other mountain tops, and everybody would get the
message. Okay, so it was a beautiful system until people sort of
broke into their communications lines and then they had to go through
a much slower process of sending out the messengers. They got hacked.
Exactly. They got hacked. They got hacked. Okay.